Okay, moving on to acute renal failure. This is an acute severe decrease in renal function,
the hallmark of which is azotemia. Azotemia refers to an increase in nitrogenous waste
products in the blood, and it's commonly measured as an increase in the BUN and the creatinine.
In addition, patients often have oliguria, and oliguria refers to low production of urine.
Now, when a patient presents with the signs and symptoms of acute renal failure,
we're going to divide the etiology into pre-renal, post-renal, and intra-renal.
We can also look at it this way. Here's the kidney, and here's the blood vessel bringing blood into the kidney,
and here's the ureter, which is draining the kidney.
One way by which we can get acute renal failure would be to decrease the blood flow.
A decrease in blood flow would result in acute renal failure, and we call that pre-renal azotemia.
Another way by which we can develop acute renal failure would be to block the outflow,
and if we block the outflow, then that would result in a back pressure in the kidney,
which would decrease the GFR of the kidney, which would then, of course, result in acute renal failure.
We call that post-renal azotemia.
And finally, we could have problems within the kidney that could result in renal failure,
and we'd call that intra-renal azotemia.
Focusing on each of these individually, pre-renal azotemia is due to a decrease in blood flow to the kidneys,
as I've already just illustrated.
This is a relatively common cause of acute renal failure,
and the decreased blood flow is going to result in decreased GFR.
Now, of course, if there's decreased blood going to the glomerulus,
then there will be less blood filtered by the glomerulus, and so the GFR would go down.
In addition, we'd get buildup of nitrogenous waste products, or azotemia,
and a decrease in the production of urine, or oliguria.
Now, whenever a patient develops azotemia, both the BUN and the creatinine in the blood are going to rise.
However, we can use the ratio of the BUN to creatinine to try to help us nail down the exact cause of the azotemia.
For example, in the particular case of pre-renal azotemia,
the serum BUN to creatinine ratio will rise to greater than 15.
Let's illustrate this just to ensure that we understand the principle.
Here you have a tubule, and of course, BUN and creatinine are both filtered by the glomerulus.
Now, normally, what would happen is that some BUN would return to the blood.
However, creatinine does not have the ability to be resorbed.
So, therefore, the normal BUN to creatinine ratio is approximately 15.
Now, in the case of pre-renal azotemia, because there's low blood flow to the kidney,
the renin-angiotensin system will be activated.
And when the renin-angiotensin system is activated,
one of the consequences will be the release of aldosterone from the adrenal gland.
Of course, aldosterone will come back to the kidney and will cause resorption of sodium.
And along with sodium, eventually, you'll resorb water.
Now, as you resorb water, additional BUN will flow into the blood.
And as additional BUN flows into the blood,
the BUN to creatinine ratio will now become greater than 15.
And this is a particularly high-yield point to be aware of.
And that's why I spent some time illustrating it.
So, let's go back, and what we say here in the text,
we say that resorption of fluid in BUN will ensue, resulting in a BUN to creatinine ratio greater than 15.
Now, recall that in this particular case of pre-renal azotemia, we haven't damaged the tubules at all.
And so, therefore, the tubular function will remain intact.
And so, the FINA, or the fractional excretion of sodium, will be less than 1%,
indicating that the tubules are able to resorb sodium.
And similarly, the urine osmolality will be greater than 500,
indicating that the tubules have the ability to concentrate the urine.
In post-renal azotemia, you have obstruction of the urinary tract downstream from the kidney.
This decreased outflow results in a back pressure, which then decreases the GFR.
We can illustrate this as follows.
If this is the glomerulus here, and this is the tubule draining the glomerulus,
if there is a back pressure going this way, and there is a glomerular pressure going this way,
this back pressure will decrease the glomerular pressure,
so that you won't be able to filter as much.
And so, again, decreased outflow in the back pressure will result in a decreased GFR.
If there is a decreased GFR, we'll also develop azotemia, as is stated here,
because nitrogenous waste products will build up in the blood,
and we'll also develop oliguria, because, again, we won't be producing as much urine.
Now, in the very early stages of a post-renal azotemia,
there will be increased tubular pressure, which will force BUN back into the blood.
And this is going to increase the BUN to creatinine ratio.
Again, let's illustrate this.
Here's the tubule, and you're normally filtering both BUN and creatinine into the filtrate.
Now, because there's going to be a back pressure coming from the obstruction,
this back pressure will force additional BUN out into the blood.
And so the BUN to creatinine ratio in the blood will now be greater than 15.
At the same time, it's important to note that the tubular function remains intact
during the early stage of post-renal azotemia.
And so, therefore, the phenol will be less than 1%,
and the uranosmolality will be greater than 500,
both indicating that the tubules are functioning fine.
If there's long-standing obstruction, however, eventually the tubule will get damaged.
And when the tubule gets damaged, you're going to get decreased resorption of BUN,
because the resorption of BUN is dependent on an intact tubule.
Therefore, the serum BUN to creatinine ratio will now be less than 15.
Let's go back and illustrate this.
If this is the tubule, and you've got this epithelium here, which is lining the tubule,
you need the epithelium to be intact in order to resorb BUN.
So as BUN comes in and creatinine comes in,
you would normally resorb BUN so that the ratio would be 15.
However, in this particular case, you're not going to be able to resorb as much BUN,
and so, therefore, the BUN to creatinine ratio will now become less than 15.
And so that's important to note.
Now, at the same time, because you've damaged the tubules,
you're going to decrease the ability to resorb sodium.
And so here, the phenol will be greater than 2%.
In addition, you'll decrease the ability to concentrate urine,
again, because the tubules are damaged,
and so the urine osmolality will be less than 500.
Now, once you've understood pre-renal and post-renal azotemia,
we're now going to move to the intrarenal causes of azotemia.
And the first is acute tubular necrosis.
In this particular disorder, you get injury and necrosis of the tubular epithelial cells.
This is the most common cause of acute renal failure.
Now, that injury and necrosis results in necrotic cells, which then plug the tubules.
That blocks the GFR, creating an intrarenal azotemia.
Let's illustrate that here.
Here's the glomerulus.
And, of course, the glomerulus is going to filter into the tubule,
and you're well aware of the fact that the tubule is lined by these epithelial cells.
Now, imagine if we have acute tubular necrosis so that these cells die.
When these cells die, they are going to slough off here into the tubule.
And as they slough off into the tubule, they are going to block the tubule.
When there's a block in the tubule, that's going to result in a back pressure this way,
which is going to decrease the ability to generate a decent GFR.
Again, the back pressure will counteract the pressure generated by the blood
in the effort to produce a GFR.
So, again, as I've stated here in the text, the necrotic cells are going to plug the tubules.
That obstruction is then going to decrease the GFR.
Another classic hallmark that would be seen in acute tubular necrosis
is the presence of dirty brown granular casts in the urine.
Now, again, the idea here is that if this is the tubule,
and the tubule is normally lined by epithelial cells,
in acute tubular necrosis, these epithelial cells, they die.
And as they die, they come into the tubule, they obstruct the tubule,
but then they get casted in the shape of the tubule,
so that when they come out in the urine,
you actually see a cast with all of these individual epithelial cells making up the cast.
Now, those epithelial cells are dead, and so they look brown and granular,
and so we call that a brown granular cast,
and that's what's going to be seen in the urine.
We can also illustrate acute tubular necrosis using this histologic image.
Here's the glomerulus, and each of these are tubules that I'm highlighting here.
This is probably the most normal tubule in the image,
and notice that these cells have nuclei,
and that the cells are up against their basement membrane.
Now, in acute tubular necrosis, the cells die,
and so you lose the nuclei, as you would expect in necrosis,
and in addition, you get detachment of the cells, notice here, from their basement membrane.
Of course, this results in sloughing of the cells into the tubule,
which then eventually would get casted in the shape of a dirty brown granular cast.
And also, of course, the plugging of these tubules by the necrotic cells
would create a back pressure, which would decrease the GFR.
Now, in this particular case, we're going to have a dysfunctional tubular epithelium,
and so therefore, we're not going to be able to resorb BUN,
and so the BUN to creatinine ratio will be less than 15.
I've already illustrated this earlier.
Also, because we don't have good tubular function,
we're going to have decreased resorption of sodium, so the phenol will be greater than 2%,
and an inability to concentrate the urine, so the urine osmolality will be less than 500.
Now, when we have acute tubular necrosis, there are two major etiologies.
There's an ischemic etiology and a nephrotoxic etiology.
In ischemic acute tubular necrosis, we decrease the blood supply,
and that's what results in the necrosis of the tubules.
Now, recall that the tubules are particularly dependent on blood supply
because of the amount of work that they have to do.
So, there's a tremendous amount of ATP that's required by the tubule,
especially the proximal renal tubule,
along with the medullary segment of the thick ascending limb.
These are particularly susceptible to ischemia.
Now, note here one last thing, and that is, in ischemic acute tubular necrosis,
it's usually going to be preceded by prerenal azotemia.
You decrease the blood flow, you get a prerenal azotemia.
As the blood flow remains decreased for an extended period of time,
that eventually progresses to ischemic acute tubular necrosis.
In nephrotoxic acute tubular necrosis, you also get necrosis of the tubular epithelial cells.
However, in this particular case, it's due to toxic agents.
And again, the proximal tubule is particularly susceptible.
Now, some of the important causes of nephrotoxic acute tubular necrosis include
amino glycosides, and you're well aware from your pharmacology studies
that amino glycosides can cause renal damage.
Heavy metals can do it.
For example, lead poisoning can cause an acute tubular necrosis.
Myoglobinuria can do it.
Patients who have crush injury, they release myoglobin into the blood,
and that can damage the kidney, causing an acute tubular necrosis.
Ethylene glycol is a classic example.
Recall that ethylene glycol is basically antifreeze,
and it could be taken by accident, for example, if a child were to consume it.
Remember that ethylene glycol has a blue color and tastes sweet.
And so sometimes children can think of it as a juice, and they might drink it,
which would then result in an acute tubular necrosis.
It's also important to note that patients who are exposed to ethylene glycol
often develop oxalate crystals in their urine.
And again, that's particularly high yield for examinations.
Radiocontrast dye can also create an acute tubular necrosis.
And then finally, urate can also do it.
Now, the classic example of a urate nephropathy would be
where patients undergo tumor lysis syndrome.
So, for example, if a patient has an acute leukemia,
and you treat them with chemotherapy,
that chemotherapy is going to rapidly kill
the large amount of cells that are floating around in the blood.
And so that rapid death of the cells results in rapid breakdown of nuclear material,
which increases the uric acid levels.
Of course, that uric acid could then damage the tubules via acute tubular necrosis.
Therefore, in order to avoid this tumor lysis syndrome,
what we often do is we hydrate the patients
to make sure that there's good flow going through the urine.
And we can also use allopyrinol, of course,
to prevent the formation of uric acid.
Now, clinically, when patients have an acute tubular necrosis,
you're going to get oliguria,
again, because you've blocked the ability of the kidney
to generate a decent GFR by plugging the tubules.
At the same time, you're going to see brown granular casts
in the urine, as I've already illustrated.
At the same time, we're going to see brown granular casts in the urine,
as I've already illustrated.
Now, the BUN and creatinine will both rise.
Of course, if you're not able to create a GFR,
you're not going to be able to filter out the BUN and creatinine from the blood.
And finally, the patients will develop hyperkalemia
with a metabolic acidosis.
The hyperkalemia is due to the fact
that you get decreased renal excretion of potassium.
And the metabolic acidosis is due to the fact
that you get decreased excretion of organic acids.
And so, actually, this acidosis would be associated
with an increased anion gap.
Now, acute tubular necrosis is reversible.
The tubular cells do have the ability to regenerate.
However, this often requires supportive dialysis
because the electrolyte imbalances generated during ATN can be fatal.
It's important to note, however,
that the allegoria that the patients experience
can actually persist for two to three weeks
before they actually recover.
Now, the reason for this is that the tubular cells,
especially the proximal tubular cell, is a stable cell.
And remember from our earlier discussions from general pathology
that stable cells are cells that have the ability
to reenter cell cycle but are currently out of cell cycle.
And so, it takes a little bit of time for the tubular cell
to actually reenter cell cycle and then eventually regenerate.
Another important cause of intrarenal azotemia
is acute interstitial nephritis.
Now, the word interstitium implies that we're dealing
with the connective tissue between the tubules.
That's what interstitium is.
It's all that connective tissue between the tubules.
And, of course, there's inflammation.
This is basically a drug-induced hypersensitivity reaction
of the interstitium.
It can spread over into the tubules.
The key causes are going to be drugs.
They include NSAIDs, penicillin, and diuretics,
just to list a few.
Here's an image just highlighting the idea.
Notice that these are tubules, and the tubules look fine.
However, what's going on here is that you've got
an inflammatory infiltrate in the connective tissue
or the interstitium between the tubules.
This inflammatory infiltrate will then result in
an acute renal failure.
Now, the presentation is oliguria, again,
because there is a renal failure with fever and rash
that arises days to weeks after starting the inciting drug.
One of the very high-yield, almost pathognomonic findings
of acute interstitial nephritis is that eosinophils
will be present, and those eosinophils may be seen
in the urine.
Of course, this is a hypersensitivity reaction,
so it will resolve with cessation of the drug.
However, it can progress to renal papillary necrosis
where the papillae of the kidney actually necrose.
Now, in renal papillary necrosis, again,
you get necrosis of the renal papillae.
This presents with gross hematuria and flank pain,
and there are a few important causes to be aware of.
The first is chronic analgesic abuse.
For example, long-term finacetin or aspirin
can result in a renal papillary necrosis.
Other causes include diabetes, sickle cell disease or trait,
and severe acute pyelonephritis.
So this concludes our section on acute renal failure.